Matías Bettera Marcat

I am a Physicist currently finishing a PhD. Researching in biophysics, and interested in science and technology. I am looking forward to a career in Data Science and Machine Learning. Linux, Open and Free software enthusiast.

Email / LinkedIN / GitHub / online resume / resume.pdf

Personal Info and links

Date of birth: March 16, 1990
Residence: Córdoba, Argentina
Cellphone: +54 (9) 358 4834287
mailto: bettera.marcat@gmail.com

SKILLS

- Programming Languages: Python, Fortran, C, Shell Scripting
- Tools & Libraries: pandas, Numpy, malplotlib, Github, Docker, Gnuplot, Bash
- LANGUAGES
 - English: Good redaction skills and fluency.
 - Spanish: Mother tongue. Advanced redaction skills and fluency.

EDUCATION

- 2020 **Data Science and its applications diploma** Mathematics, Astronomy, Physics and Computer Science school, National University of Córdoba, Argentina.
- 2016 **PhD in Physics**, research on Dynamics of microconfined swimmers. Mathematichs, Astronomy, Physics and Computer Science school, National University of Córdoba, Argentina. (*Doctorado en Físca. FaMAF, UNC. Investigación: Dinámica de nadadores microconfinados, FaMAF, UNC*).
 - PhD Courses: Numerical Methods in Astrophysics, Computational Physics, Fluid Mechanics, Topics in Mathematical Biology, Introduction to LAMMPS code.
- 2010-2016 **B.S. in Physics**, Final grad work: Simultaneous uptake model of water and nutrients by crop roots. Physics department, National University of Rio Cuarto, Argentina. (*Licenciatura en Física, Trabajo Final: Modelo de toma simultánea de agua y nutrientes por raíces de cultivos. UNRC*)

EXPERIENCE

- Lecturer, Mathematics, Astronomy, Physics and Computer Science school, National University of Córdoba, Argentina. (Profesor Ayudante B D.S., FaMAF, UNC.)
 - **08/2022 to -** Mechanics
 - **03/2022 to 07/2022** Admission and introductory course.
- Lecturer, National University of Rio Cuarto, Argentina.
 - \circ 08/2022 to General Physics III (Electricity and Magnetism)
 - o 03/2022 to 07/2022 Thermodynamics and Statistical Mechanics I
 - **03/2016 to 07/2016** General Physics IV (Waves and Optics)
- Research fellowship, granted by CONICET. (Beca Interna Doctoral de CONICET)
 - 04/2016 to 03/2022 Research on active matter, particularly sperm dynamics in confined environments, with simulations and experimental data analysis. (Investigación sobre materia activa, en particular dinámica de espermátozoides en ambientes confinados, con simulaciones y análisis de datos experimentales.)
- Student assistant, Physics department, National University of Rio Cuarto, Argentina. (Alumno Ayudante de Segunda D.S. FCEFQyN, UNRC.)
 - o 03/2015 to 07/2015 Electromagnetism I
 - **08/2014 to 12/2014** General Physics I (Introduction to Mechanics)
 - o 03/2013 to 07/2013 Mechanics
 - o 08/2012 to 12/2012 Electromagnetism I

PUBLICATIONS

- Hitting the wall: Human sperm velocity recovery under ultra-confined conditions. Bettera Marcat M. A. *et al.* Biomicrofluidics **14**(2), 024108 (2020). [Link]
- Espermatozoides microconfinados: interacción con paredes. Bettera Marcat M. A. et al. Anales AFA **29**(4), 111-115 (2018). [Link]
- Validación de un modelo de toma de simultánea de agua y nutrientes. Bettera Marcat M. A. et al. Anales AFA 28(2), 37-40 (2017).[Link]